I had a fire nine days ago.
منذ تسعة أيام ، حصل لي حريق
My archive:
إرشيفي:
175 films, my 16-millimeter negative,
175 فيلمًا ، النيغاتيف ذو ال16 مليمترًا
all my books, my dad's books, my photographs.
جميع كتبي و كتب والدي
I'd collected --
التي جمعتها --
I was a collector, major, big-time.
لفترة طويلة من الوقت كنت أجمع --
It's gone.
جميعها ذهبت
I just looked at it,
نظرت إليها
and I didn't know what to do.
و لم أعرف ماذا سأفعل
I mean, this was --
أعني.. لقد كان هذا ..
was I my things?
هل كنت أعيش بين مقتنياتي؟
I always live in the present -- I love the present.
أعيش دومًا في الحاضر -- أحب الحاضر
I cherish the future.
أعز المستقبل .
And I was taught some strange thing as a kid,
لقد تعلمت في صغري بعض الأشياء الغريبة ،
like, you've got to make something good out of something bad.
مثل: عليك القيام بصنع شيء جيد من آخر سيء .
You've got to make something good out of something bad.
عليك صنع شيء جيد من آخر سيء .
This was bad! Man, I was --
لقد كان هذا سيئًا ! يارجل، كنت --
I cough. I was sick.
كنت أسعل. كنت مريضًا
That's my camera lens. The first one --
تلك عدسات كاميرتي. أول كاميرا --
the one I shot my Bob Dylan film with 35 years ago.
التي صورت بها فيلم "بوب ديلان" منذ 35 عامًا
That's my feature film. "King, Murray"
هذا فيلمي الروائي "الملك موراي"
won Cannes Film Festival 1970 --
الذي ربح جائزة مهرجان كان السينمائي لعام 1970
the only print I had.
النسخة الوحيدة التي أمتلكها
That's my papers.
هذه أوراقي
That was in minutes -- 20 minutes.
حصل ذلك في غضون دقائق -- 20 دقيقة
Epiphany hit me. Something hit me.
فجأة أدركت شيء ما ، شيء ما أصابني
"You've got to make something good out of something bad,"
"عليك صنع شيء جيد من آخر سيء"
I started to say to my friends, neighbors, my sister.
بدأت أرددها على أصدقائي و جيراني و أختي
By the way, that's "Sputnik." I ran it last year.
بالمناسبة، هذا "سباتنيك: القمر الصناعي"، صورته العام المنصرم
"Sputnik" was downtown, the negative. It wasn't touched.
سباتنيك، النيجاتيف كان في وسط المدينة لم يلمس. لم يصبها أي سوء
These are some pieces of things I used in my Sputnik feature film,
هذه بعض القطع من أغراضٍ كنت قد استخدمتها في فيلمي الروائي "سباتنيك"
which opens in New York in two weeks
و الذي تم افتتاحه في نيويورك منذ أسبوعين
downtown.
في وسط المدينة .
I called my sister. I called my neighbors. I said, "Come dig."
اتصلت بأختي، اتصلت بالجيران ، قلت لهم: "تعالوا ابحثوا"
That's me at my desk.
هذا أنا في مكتبي
That was a desk took 40-some years to build.
مكتب استغرق 40 عاماً من البناء
You know -- all the stuff.
تعرفون -- بقية الأشياء
That's my daughter, Jean.
هذه ابنتي، جين
She came. She's a nurse in San Francisco.
جاءت، وهي تعمل ممرضة في سان فرانسيسكو
"Dig it up," I said. "Pieces.
قلت "ابحثوا". "القطع.
I want pieces. Bits and pieces."
أريد القطع. القطع و الأجزاء"
I came up with this idea: a life of bits and pieces,
جئت بهذه الفكرة: حياة من القطع و الأجزاء،
which I'm just starting to work on -- my next project.
و التي بدأت بالعمل عليها -- مشروعي القادم.
That's my sister. She took care of pictures,
هذه أختي، اهتمت بالصور ،
because I was a big collector of snapshot photography
كنت جامعًا كبيرًا للقطات الفوتوغرافية
that I believed said a lot.
و التي تقول الكثير باعتقادي .
And those are some of the pictures that --
و هذه بعض الصور التي --
something was good about the burnt pictures.
شيء ما كان جيدًا حيال الصور المحترقة .
I didn't know. I looked at that --
لم أكن أعلم. نظرت إليها--
I said, "Wow, is that better than the --"
قلت " ياللروعة، أهذا أفضل من --"
That's my proposal on Jimmy Doolittle. I made that movie for television.
هذا عرضي لمشروع جيمي دوليتل. لقد صنعت الفيلم للتلفاز .
It's the only copy I had. Pieces of it.
إنها النسخة الوحيدة التي أمتلكها -- أجزاء منها .
Idea about women.
فكرة حول النساء .
So I started to say, "Hey, man, you are too much!
بدأت أقول " يا رجل، أنت تبالغ كثيرًا!
You could cry about this." I really didn't.
قد تبكي لأجل هذا" في الواقع لم أبكي .
I just instead said,
بدلاً عنه قلت،
"I'm going to make something out of it, and maybe next year ... "
" سأصنع شيئًا منه، ربما العام القادم.."
And I appreciate this moment
و أنا ممتن لهذه اللحظة
to come up on this stage with so many people
للصعود على هذا المسرح مع الكثير من الأشخاص
who've already given me so much solace,
الذين منحوني الكثير من السلوان
and just say to TEDsters:
و أقول لمجتمع تيد:
I'm proud of me. That I take something bad,
أنا فخور بنفسي. لأني حصلت على شيء سيء
I turn it, and I'm going to make something good out of this,
و قلبته، و سأقوم بعمل شيء جيد منه.
all these pieces.
كل هذه الأجزاء .
That's Arthur Leipzig's original photograph I loved.
هذه صورة أصلية أحببتها لآرثر ليبزيغ
I was a big record collector --
كنت جامعًا للإسطوانات
the records didn't make it. Boy, I tell you,
الإسطوانات لم تنجو. أخبركم
film burns. Film burns.
الفيلم احترق، الفيلم احترق
I mean, this was 16-millimeter safety film.
أعني، هذا كان فيلم ناجٍ ذو 16-ملليمترًا
The negatives are gone.
النيغاتيف احترق .
That's my father's letter to me, telling me to
هذه رسالة والدي إليّ، يخبرني فيها
marry the woman I first married when I was 20.
أن أتزوج المرأة التي كانت زوجتي الأولى حين كان عمري 20 سنة
That's my daughter and me.
هذه ابنتي و أنا
She's still there. She's there this morning, actually.
لا تزال هناك. في الحقيقة، إنها هناك هذا الصباح
That's my house.
هذا هو بيتي .
My family's living in the Hilton Hotel in Scotts Valley.
عائلتي تقطن في فندق الهيلتون بسكوت فالي .
That's my wife, Heidi,
هذه زوجتي، هايدي ،
who didn't take it as well as I did.
و التي لم تتحمل الصدمة كما فعلت .
My children, Davey and Henry.
أطفالي، ديفي و هنري .
My son, Davey, in the hotel two nights ago.
ابني، ديفي في الفندق منذ ليلتين.
So, my message to you folks,
رسالتي إليكم أيها الرفاق ،
from my three minutes, is that I appreciate the chance
من الثلاث دقائق خاصتي، إنني ممتن لهذه الفرصة
to share this with you. I will be back. I love being at TED.
لأشارككم هذا. سأعود لاحقًا. أحب أن أكون هنا في تيد .
I came to live it, and I am living it.
أتيت لأعيشها و ها أنا أعيشها الآن.
That's my view from my window outside of Santa Cruz, in Bonny Doon,
هذا المنظر من نافذتي بسانتا كروز في بوني دون ،
just 35 miles from here.
تبعد مسافة 35 ميلاً من هنا.
Thank you everybody.
شكرًا لكم جميعًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)